Register of the Firing Line (Television Program) broadcast records 80040.4089238
Hoover Institution Archives
- Episode Guide, 1966-1999
  - "Cutting Your Taxes" Guests: Kemp, Jack.: Greenfield, Jeff., 24 April 1978 (Item Program Number S0321, 741)
    Program details: It's hard to remember now that the Kemp-Roth bill pre-dated the Reagan Administration, but so it did. An engaging hour with the young Jack Kemp, who, as WFB puts it in his introduction, had "helped to develop the most welcome political proposal conceivable: eat a greater portion of the cake, so as to increase the size of it." One sample: JK: "If you shrank a year's behavior into one week, and if you taxed Monday's income at 10 per cent, Tuesday's at 20 per cent, Wednesday's at 30 per cent, and so on, then you have to ask the question at what point during the week would leisure become more attractive ... than work? At what point would a tax shelter look far more attractive than an investment in a factory or an entrepreneurial activity?" WFB: "You'd start getting pretty long weekends, wouldn't you?" JK: "You'd get very long weekends."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.566
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6500
  - "The Holocaust Controversy" Guests: O'Connor, John J.: Neusner, Jacob, 1932-, 12 May 1978 (Item Program Number S0322, 742)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 114: 33
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 16
    Program details: A docudrama called "Holocaust" had just aired on NBC to wide acclaim--but not the acclaim of WFB and his guests, who proceed to discuss it with depth and authority. JN: "I think we are dealing with an event that has been exploited so that what happened along time ago--" WFB: "Exploited in what sense? You don't mean commercially exploited, do you? Or do you?" JN: "Well, I think that's not the principal kind of exploitation. There's been a political and an emotional exploitation of tragic events that are rich in human meaning. This is something that some of us have been calling Holocaust Inc., because we are confronted now with the turning of a human tragedy of almost infinite dimensions into a club with which to beat the world." WFB: "Or to beat God." ... JJO: "The defenders of Holocaust keep coming back to the same old theme: it was better to have it on than not have it on. Why? ... For some reason they feel that if you put this on there's going to be a massive change in the thinking of the population."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.567
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6501
  - "Public Policy and the Economy" Guests: Simon, William E., 1927-: Shilling, A. Gary., 12 May 1978 (Item Program Number S0323, 743)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 114: 34
    Program details: We were in the midst of the "stagflation" (stagnation combined with inflation) that would two years thence be part of the reason for President Carter's defeat; but at this point our guests are voices crying in the wilderness, "attempting to explain to the American people," as Mr. Simon puts it, "whom I consider, at risk of offending them, economically illiterate," that "economic freedoms and personal and political freedoms are indivisible, that when the government takes over your substance it takes power over your liberty." An electric discussion of, to quote again from Mr. Simon, "the pattern [of] spend and spend, elect and elect, tax, regulate, and dominate our lives and our livelihoods."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.568
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6502
  - "The Psychological Society" Guests: Gross, Martin L. (Martin Louis), 1925-: Tamarkin, Norman R., 31 May 1978 (Item Program Number S0324, 744)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 114: 35
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 17
    Program details: As the title of Mr. Gross's book suggests, he doesn't think much of modern psychiatry, which in his view is "neglecting the comparatively few people who really need its services, in favor of taking care of the well people on Park Avenue or Miami Beach." Dr. Tamarkin maintains that on the whole the profession is honest about differentiating between clinical conditions and normal grief or anxiety. Mr. Buckley serves as referee. NRT (alleging that Mr. Gross has misquoted certain people in his book): "Dr. Greenson is not aloof, according to him. He talks to his patients regularly--" MG: "Excuse me--" NRT: "--and if you have some strange idea of--" MG: "If Dr. Greenson were to admit this in public he'd be discharged from the American Psychoanalytic--" NRT:"That's--" MG: "--because classical analysis is based on incognito, as you know. Aloofness and--" NRT: "That's hard and extreme [and] rarely practiced, Martin, and he wouldn't be kicked out of the American Psychoanalytic-- That's foolishness you're saying." MG: "No, that's not true. Dr. Greenson has written a text which says specifically, and please read the text again, that psychoanalysis is a cool, detached, objective analysis. It is not normal psychotherapy, which Dr. Freud says was dross, and psychoanalysis was golden." WFB: "Let me try to get concrete."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.569
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6503
  - "The Crisis of Intelligence" Guests: Walters, Vernon A.: Meyer, Sylvan, 31 May 1978 (Item Program Number S0325, 745)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 114: 36
    Program details: General Walters had, roughly speaking, been everywhere and seen everything for three decades--confidential translator for Presidents Truman, Eisenhower, and Kennedy; CIA man and ambassador to the United Nations; witness to the Smoking Gun conversation that brought Watergate to a close. On this show--which ranges from Pearl Harbor back to the American Revolution and forward again to Watergate and to a world scene that includes, as General Walters puts it, "42,000 Cubans spread around Africa today"--he proves incisive and impressive: "My own position on assassination is that I am against it for three reasons: (1) It's against the law of God. (2) It's against the law of man. (3) It doesn't work." WFB: "Which shows that God was prudent?" VW: "Very. We know that." Note: Alternate title on transcript is "Secret Diplomacy."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.570
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00ANCWR4W
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6504
  - "Numbering error -- repeat of Firing Line #S298" Guests:, 0000-00-00 (Item Program Number S0326)
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 18
    Program details:
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.542
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6476
  - "[A Firing Line Debate]: Resolved: That We Welcome the Growth of the Public Sector" Guests: Harrington, Michael, 1928-: Buckley, William F. (William Frank), 1925-2008., 13 October 1977 (Item Program Number S0327, 801)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 1
    Program details: Like Firing Line s0317, this is a formal debate but with a single combatant on either side. Mr. Harrington contends that "certain hard facts--an aging population; the growth of technology and of pollution-force an increase in the public sector whether anyone likes it or not: Okay. Mr. Buckley and I agree: inexorably, under a Nixon, under a Ford, the government moves in. Why? Why is that historical trend there? Is it there because of a plot? Is it there because Nixon or Ford or whatever conservative gets in sells out? I don't think so. I think there are profound economic, social, technological, and political trends which force conservatives as well as liberals to advocate more government intervention." ... WFB: "Government got into medicine about 12 years ago. What has happened? Do we have more doctors? No. Do we have more nurses? No. What we have is double the cost of a medical bill."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.543
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6477
  - "The Sinking Dollar" Guests: Healey, Denis., 26 June 1978 (Item Program Number S0328, 802)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 2
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 19
    Program details: A crackling exchange that doesn't have a lot to do with the sinking dollar mentioned in the title (DH: "My dear fellow, I have enough trouble running our own economy not to make judgments about yours") but that ranges over government deficits and North Sea oil, comparative standards of living ("I think that we in Britain have always valued material things less than social stability, comfort, ease, grace. I would say the change in Britain since the war is exactly the opposite one: that having declined relative to other countries for a century,... [since] 1960 I think Britain has given more, not less, attention to material things"), and the relation between taxation and wage increases (with Mr. Healey defending a 98 per cent top tax rate on the grounds that "if you're to get the consent of people with very low living standards not to ... bargain for excessive wages and to settle for moderate increases, then you have to prove to them that other people are subject to similar limitations").
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.571
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6505
  - "Numbering error -- repeat of Firing Line #S318" Guests:, 0000-00-00 (Item Program Number S0329)
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.563
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6497
  - "The 1950s Communist Purge" Guests: Caute, David., 26 June 1978 (Item Program Number S0330, 803)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 3
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 20
    Program details: This show offers a clash of world views between WFB and a man whose book had been criticized even by so dedicated an anti-McCarthyite as Arthur Schlesinger Jr., on the grounds that it somehow suggests "that... it was a wicked thing to call a Stalinist a Stalinist or a fellow traveler a fellow traveler." DC: "It all depends on what our premises about a national consensus are. To many people the victory of the Red Army or Mao Tse-tung's Communist regime in China in 1949 was not the collapse of China, nor, to use the phrase you used rather significantly a moment ago, was it a question of 'we,' the United States, 'lost China.'..." WFB: "But you see, Mr. Caute, in America we have a system in which there are branches of government, and it is the explicit constitutional responsibility of the Congress of the United States to monitor the activities of the Executive. Now, one of the activities of the Executive was to engage in a series of maneuvers in the Far East which, assuming a causal relationship of any sort, resulted in the enslavement by the Communists of the Mainland and in a war in Korea in which a great many Americans were killed."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.572
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6506
  - "The Rhodesian Dilemma" Guests: Muzorewa, Abel Tendekayi, 1925-, 21 July 1978 (Item Program Number S0331, 804)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 4
    Program details: "Bishop Muzorewa," as WFB introduces him, "has been ... the outstanding leader in Rhodesia, demanding political rights for the black majority. He eschewed violence, insisting on other forms of pressure. He pursued Christian principles." But in Western establishment opinion he had fallen from grace by joining (with two other black leaders) in a Provisional Council with Prime Minister Ian Smith, to shepherd Rhodesia through what they hoped would be a peaceful transition. Revolutionaries led by Joshua Nkomo and Robert Mugabe were waging guerrilla warfare, "with the explicit goal," as WFB puts it, "of frustrating the national plebiscite and creating an all-black Marxist-oriented state." So why aren't Americans rallying behind the moderates? Bishop Muzorewa gives us a richly detailed account of postwar African political history, including the terms on which, say, Tanganyika and Zambia got their independence, and how that affects their attitudes towards present-day Rhodesia: "Your State Department... I believe is acting ... to appease certain powers in Africa ... [who] have one person they have decided should be the king of Zimbabwe and they are trying to be kingmakers themselves. This started with Dr. Kaunda [President of Zambia], who is personally committed to Mr. Nkomo, and he has mobilized every front-line state, so called, to support him."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.578
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B003GXE9SC
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6512
  - "Muggeridge Revisited" Guests: Muggeridge, Malcolm, 1903-1990.: Knight, Andrew., 27 June 1978 (Item Program Number S0332, 805)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 5
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 21
    Program details: The last time Mr. Muggeridge was on Firing Line, Mr. Buckley reminds us, it was to comment on Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn's first television interview (#S225); a few weeks before today's show was taped, Solzhenitsyn had again made waves, this time with his Harvard commencement address. Solzhenitsyn, with those great burning eyes, speaks like a prophet. Muggeridge, with his twinkling eyes, speaks like a benevolent grandfather-but the two men wind up saying much the same thing, whether speaking of the City of God or the City of Man. MM: Every courageous man in the West who believes in freedom and equality will have a go at them [the South Africans], because that's very easy. But-" WFB: "Or Chile." MM: "Chile, not quite so easily, because there aren't many black people there, and it's not within the orbit much of the West; but South Africa is the absolutely favorite thing. In order not to have to do or say anything about the Gulag, it's perfect.... I've been reading Spengler in these dark days. Do you ever read it?" WFB: "I've managed to avoid it." MM: "You won't avoid it for long.""
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.574
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6508
  - "Firing Line's British Correspondents" Guests: Hayman, Helene Middleweek.: Evans, Roger.: Riddell, Peter., 27 June 1978 (Item Program Number S0333, 806)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 6
    Program details: It had been ten years since these three Britons had first appeared on Firing Line--in that case, as panelists when they were all three still at Cambridge. They have jointly and severally appeared many times since as panelists or guest interrogators; it was thought this time to invite them as guests in their own right. They come through splendidly, in a spirited examination of the differences between British and American public-affairs television and political debate (with an account of, among much else, how Enoch Powell had finally broken the barrier of silence against him on British TV), the adversary tradition in debating, and the merits of public speakers from Edmund Burke to Richard Nixon. One sample: WFB: "Are you supposed to memorize your speech [in the House of Commons]?" HMH: "You're supposed to speak impromptu." WFB: "Well, the great orations of Churchill--as a matter of fact, he did memorize them; but a number... For instance, the speeches of Burke were certainly not impromptu, were they?" RE: "He always emptied the House of Commons. He was known as the dinner bell. He was not a successful parliamentary orator. Lord North was the parliamentary genius of his age, which is why he preserved his majority so long in the face of the rebellion in the Americas; and so was Walpole before him. That was a knockabout House of Commons, impromptu style."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.573
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6507
  - "Cambodia and the Refugee Problem" Guests: Vin, Im.: Cherne, Leo, 1912-, 20 July 1978 (Item Program Number S0334, 807)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 7
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 22
    Program details: The holocaust in Cambodia had been going on for three years; somewhere between 15 and 25 per cent of the population had been killed. Mr. Vin had escaped to tell the tale, and although his English is weak, he is a moving witness ("I don't think that what is reported to the world is exaggerated. What is said about the holocaust, the executions, the crimes, starvation, hardship, and sickness, is true, absolutely true"). To the question why are so many people denying the magnitude of the killing, Mr. Cherne points out that some of those who were initially the most skeptical (partly because of "their previous knowledge of the Cambodians as a gentle people; and it seemed inconceivable to them"), once they saw the evidence, "are today the most impressive among those who have assembled the data which make Mr. Vin's story a modest one."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.576
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6510
  - "What Rights Do Nazis Have?" Guests: Dershowitz, Alan M.: Neier, Aryeh, 1937-: Van den Haag, Ernest., 20 July 1978 (Item Program Number S0335, 808)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 8
    Program details: The American Nazi Party had sought to march in the predominantly Jewish town of Skokie, Illinois, and finally had been permitted instead to march in a park in Chicago; many people had been surprised--or indeed infuriated--when the ACLU weighed in on behalf of the Nazis. Host and guests, approaching free speech from four quite different directions, shed considerable light on the bases for maintaining free speech and the theories on when it can be justifiably curtailed. One sample: WFB: "Would you defend the right of the American people by constitutional amendment to repeal the Bill of Rights?" AN: "No, because I don't derive my civil-liberties values from the Bill of Rights. I consider it fortunate that the Bill of Rights embodies the civil-liberties values that I hold, but the values come first; the particular instrument come second."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.575
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6509
  - "Three vs. William F. Buckley Jr." Guests: Pilpel, Harriet F.: Burden, Carter.: Lowenstein, Allard K., 21 July 1978 (Item Program Number S0336, 809)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 9-10
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 23
    Program details: In this installment of the semi-annual turning of the tables, the guests question their host on everything from government spending, to the Equal Rights Amendment and abortion, to aid to authoritarian regimes. Two samples: HP: "I think what we can agree on in disputes of this kind is that the role of the government, in a culturally diverse, pluralistic society, is to be neutral." WFB: "My God! You want to pass a law [ERA] forbidding me to hire a female nurse for my mother, and you're telling me the law has to be neutral in matters of such gravity as abortion!" ... CB: "But if life is sacred, if that is a basic moral premise, then how can you in any case justify taking life [via the death penalty]?" WFB: "By reading the Bible." CB: "An eye for an eye? You subscribe to that?" WFB: "No, I don't subscribe to that. But there are many instances in the Bible where, given due process, and given the gravity of the crime, the taking of life is authorized."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.577
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001E52U9O
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6511
  - "Federal Regulation and the Travel Explosion" Guests: Kahn, Alfred E. (Alfred Edward), 22 August 1978 (Item Program Number S0337, 810)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 11
    Program details: Mr. Kahn is that rare bird, a regulator who wants his regulatory agency to go out of business (which it eventually did, though not on his watch--Firing Line s0631). He is another breed of rare bird as well: a public servant who speaks plain, and pungent, English. A spirited conversation exploring what is the minimal sort of regulation that is needed in the air lanes, why the government shouldn't be granting monopoly routes, and how competition really can work in the airline industry. HK: "In any case, American Airlines, which was one of the leading objectors to deregulation, has now gone all the way over to the other extreme." WFB: "With cut fares and cut rates." HK: "Oh yes. They just say, 'Get out of our way.' I wish I could say that I had been farsighted enough to have planned it so, but there is a general view now among many airline executives that if the CAB is going to be of so little use to us by way of protecting us, then let's get them out of the way. That is a simply delightful development."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.579
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6513
  - "Newsmen and the Law" Guests: Worthington, Peter, 1927-: Rusher, William A., 1923-, 22 August 1978 (Item Program Number S0338, 811)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 12
    Transcript: Box/Folder 174: 24
    Program details: Mr. Worthington had been arraigned under the Official Secrets Act--ostensibly because he had published confidential Royal Canadian Mounted Police documents detailing KGB activity; or possibly, WFB posits, because he was such a trenchant critic of the Trudeau government. A bracing discussion of the rights and responsibilities of journalists. WFB: T"he Pentagon Papers case, for instance-where would you have voted on that?" PW: "Oh, but you see, I don't have much use for the Daniel Ellsbergs of this world. It seems to me they're violating the spirit of their oath (if there was an oath). However, as a journalist, if I had the opportunity to receive the papers, I would publish them. Police don't have to admire the informer while using his information."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.580
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6514
  - "The Mission of the Pope" Guests: Martin, Malachi., 6 September 1978 (Item Program Number S0339, 812)
    Background File: Box/Folder 97; 3
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 115: 13